再读一遍
Read this again.
行了，雷
这是个很棒的礼物
Come on, Ray.
Honey, it's a great present.
你在这上面写的祝词
非常完美
What you wrote
on it is perfect,
就算不行你也来不及改了
因为今天已经是圣诞夜了
and you can't change it now anyway
because it's Christmas Eve.
再念一遍
Once more!
“耶诞快乐，我们爱你”
"Merry Christmas.
We love you.
“麦克、杰弗瑞、艾丽、黛博拉和雷”
Michael, Geoffrey,
Ally, Debra and Ray."
－太傻了
－哦！
￡- lt's stupid!
￡- Oh!
不，每个人都会喜欢这件礼物的，OK？
No, everybody's going to love
this present, okay?
就这样吧，你的主意棒极了
Accept it, you had
a great idea.
我为什么要写“耶诞”？
Why did l put Xmas,
you know?
我不喜欢“耶诞”
l don't like Xmas.
把寿星的名字都给省略了
l X￡-ed out the name
of the birthday boy.
雷，够了！
Ray, stop!
别再困扰了，OK？
我很喜欢它
Stop obsessing, okay?
l love it.
我的上帝啊，一个面包机说了两个月
My God, it's been
two months of toaster!
嘿，这东西送出去的时候可是刻着我的大名的
Hey, this is going out
with my name on it.
－ 送给你父母的那只包装好了吗？
－ 是的
￡- Did you wrap the one for your parents?
￡- Yes.
－ 用什么包的？
－ 箔纸
￡- Which wrapping?
￡- The foil.
不！！
No!
－ 那会透露礼物的内容！
－ 什么？
￡- That tips off the gift.
￡- What?!
箔纸包装……
这是台不锈钢面包机啊！
Foil wrapping￡-￡-
it's a metal toaster!
你还不如直接用面包机包装算了
Why don't you just
wrap it in toast?
既然我驱车一整天去康乃狄格
Look, if l'm going to drive
all the way up to Connecticut
和你的父母一起过圣诞节
to spend Christmas Day
with your parents,
我就希望看到他们打开礼物时惊喜的样子
l want a good reaction
when they open the present.
箔纸包装就没惊喜了？
And the foil wrapping
kills that?
我不知道
l don't know.
你觉得这台面包机对他们来说
够特别吗？
You think this toaster thing
is funky enough for them?
它应该臭烘烘的？
Was it supposed
to be funky?
我是说
For them, l mean￡-￡-
他们是时髦人士
they're the hip people.
哦，亲爱的
Oh, honey.
你也不落伍啊
Come on,
you're hip.
是的，这是一件非常
Yes, yes,
this is a very...
时髦的
hip...
特别的
funky...
臭屁面包机！
bad￡-ass toaster!
很好，尽管取笑我吧
very nice.
Yeah, make fun of me.
－不，我没有
－是吗？你的父母
￡- No, l'm not!
￡- Oh yeah, your parents￡-￡-
－你和你的父母一直在容忍我
－没人在容忍你
￡- your parents and you put up with me￡-￡-
￡- No, nobody feels that way.
我是个蠢蛋，OK？我承认
l'm a doofus, okay?
l admit it.
我开什么玩笑哪！看看我
Come on, who am l kidding?
Look at me.
我是个可笑的傻瓜，带着个可笑的面包机
l'm a goofy doofus
with a foofy toaster.
什么？
What?
我没事
Look, it's fine,
all right?
我不怪谁，你本来可以嫁得更好些
l'm not blaming anyone. l don't know,
you could have married better.
我不知道
l don't know.
圣诞快乐，宝贝
晚安
Merry Christmas, honey.
Good night.
噢天哪！瞧我的大鼻子！
Oh God!
Look at the size of my nose!
像威尔士人那样说：
lechyd da!
And, as the Welsh say,
嘿
Hey!
Brushum-feltya!
我现编的
l just made that up.
雷，把礼物给他们
Come on, Ray.
Let's give them our present.
他们会等我们走了才打开
You know what?
They'll open it when we leave.
别这样，马上就打开吧
Oh stop it.
No, here it is, right here.
是雷蒙德选的，一切都是他的主意
Raymond picked it out,
and he did everything.
哦，我喜欢这个包装
Oh, well l love
the wrapping!
那是黛博拉做的
Debra did that.
嘿，一个面包机
Hey, a toaster.
－看呀，一个面包机
－噢～
￡- Look, hon, a toaster.
￡- Oh.
真不错
How nice.
你们应该打开盒子
You got to open
the box.
快点拆吧
You go ahead there.
你怎么了？
What are you doing?
恨自己
Hating myself.
看哪，沃伦
Oh look, Warren!
“耶诞快乐，我们爱你”
"Merry Christmas.
We love you.
“麦克、杰弗瑞、艾丽、黛博拉和雷”
Michael, Geoffrey,
Ally, Debra and Ray."
太棒了
This is fantastic!
看到了？
你们很喜欢，对不对？
You see?
You love it, right?
－多妙的主意啊，谁想出来的？
－雷
￡- What a wild idea. Who thought of this?
￡- Ray.
不……我
No, well￡-￡- l￡-￡-
没错
Yeah, yeah.
哦，雷蒙德
Oh, Raymond.
看看那刻字
Look at that engraving.
我喜欢镀铬
l love the chrome.
太棒了！真的太棒了！
Super! Just super!
谢谢你，谢谢你，雷
Thank you. Thank you, thank you,
thank you, Ray!
真是优雅而别致
lt is so retro￡-chic!
你在拿我开玩笑，是不是？
You're making
fun of me, right?
不，这个应该展览一下
No, this should be
on display.
全垒打，看到了吧？
Home run. See?
－看看谁来了！
－呵呵呵
￡- Look who's here!
￡- Ho ho ho!
嘿，罗伯特
真高兴你来
Hey, Robert!
So glad you made it!
－我还以为你不来了
－我们正打算回去
￡- l thought you weren't gonna come.
￡- lt was on the way back.
我刚和朋友去滑雪了
l was doing some skiing
with a friend.
－她来了
－嗨
￡- Here she comes.
￡- Hi.
－圣诞快乐
－林恩，大家
￡- Merry Christmas.
￡- Leann, everyone.
－大家，林恩
－欢迎
￡- Everyone, Leann.
￡- Welcome.
进来吧，把大衣给我
Come in.
Let me take your coat.
小日子过得挺滋润嘛
What is your life now?
还可以吧～
l don't know.
Better?
对了，你送我的面包机真不错
Hey, by the way, that toaster
you gave me, it was great.
我特地来夸你的
把名字都刻上了
l gotta hand it to you,
all the names engraved.
真的？谢谢
Yeah?
Thanks.
哦，真好啊
Oh, that was so sweet.
我的兄弟们只会给我
一些便宜的浴盐
All my brother gave me
was some cheap bath salts.
我只是想以一种……
l just wanted
to express myself in a...
优雅而别致的方式
表达自己的祝福
retro￡-chic way.
你全家都送了？
The whole family got one?
是啊，还有一些朋友们
Yeah, and a couple
of friends too.
他们都会喜欢的
They're all
gonna love it.
爸爸和妈妈那边怎么说？
Listen, what did Mom and Dad
say about the toaster?
我们正准备回去
We're heading
back there now.
我只送了他们一个软马桶垫
l only got them
a soft toilet seat.
我想我该……
l guess l'll￡-￡-
我应该，在上面写首诗什么的
l guess l'm gonna have to￡-￡-
l don't know, write a poem on it.
说真的，我过来主要是为了
No, but really,
the reason why l came by
向你说声谢谢
was to say thank you.
－ 你太费心了
－ 应该的
￡- You're sweet and thoughtful.
￡- Yeah, all right.
－ 我说真的
－ 好吧，谢谢
￡- l mean it.
￡- Well, thanks.
－圣诞快乐，雷蒙德
－是啊
￡- Merry Christmas, Raymond.
￡- Oh, yeah.
谢谢，罗比
你也是
Thanks, Robby.
You too.
看到了？你成功了
Oh see?
You did it!
完美的圣诞礼物
每个人都喜欢
The perfect present.
Everybody loves it.
天哪，这真有圣诞节的气氛，不是吗？
Oh boy, it really feels like Christmas,
doesn't it?
什么？
What?
为什么妈妈和爸爸还没为这面包机
打电话过来？
Why didn't Mom and Dad
call about the toaster?
嘿，雷
brushum-feltya!
Hey, Ray,
嘿，雷。猜猜看
guess what?
三条电话留言
Three more messages
on the machine.
盖尔、安迪、琳达
都喜欢面包机
Gayle, Andy, Linda,
all loved the toaster!
我父母那里还是没有音信
Yeah, still nothing
from my parents.
我23号给他们的，今天都26号了
l gave it to them on the 23rd.
lt's the 26th
他们既没过来，也不打电话
and they haven't called
or stopped by.
－你知道这是什么意思吗？
－什么意思？
￡- You know what that's called?
￡- What?
一个圣诞祝福
A merry Christmas!
我不觉得
l don't get it.
你给他们送了礼物，就会想着……
You give them a present,
you'll think that￡-￡-
－嗨
￡- Hi!
是时候砍倒圣诞树了
Time to take down
the tree.
－嘿，妈
－嗯？
￡- Hey, Ma?
￡- Yeah?
－ 圣诞节过得怎么样？
－ 很精彩
￡- How was your Christmas?
￡- lt was marvelous.
特而斯一家来了，我们一起唱歌
The Telsters came over
and we sang songs.
我们还喝了一些杏子酒
We even had
some Amaretto.
你真该看看你爸的样子
You should have seen
your father.
他的表演真的太精彩了
He was wonderful.
好吧
Okay.
OK，你们生气了
因为我们跟她的父母一起过圣诞节
Okay, you're mad because we spent
Christmas Day at her parents' house.
当然不是，亲爱的
Of course not, dear.
我懂得权衡利弊
l know we trade off.
不过我还是挺希望你在这儿的
l did wish
you were there, though.
你爸爸和一只垃圾桶跳舞
Your father danced
with a trash can!
是啊，精彩先生
Yeah, Mr. Wonderful!
他快活得不得了
He had the time
of his life.
－他需要一些阿司匹林，可以吗？
－当然
￡- He needs some aspirin. May l?
￡- Yeah, sure.
那么，妈
你今年得到什么好礼物了吗？
So, Ma, did you get
some nice things this year?
是的，宝贝。很不错
Oh yes, dear.
Lovely.
没什么可抱怨的
l can't complain.
好吧，你收到我的礼物了没有？
All right,
did you get my gift?
噢，收到了
亲爱的，美极了
Oh, yes, dear.
very nice.
你知道……
You know￡-￡-
我听说你碰到了罗比的滑雪女伴
l heard that you met
Robby's skiing date.
你觉得她怎么样？
Did you like her?
我去和爸爸谈
l'm talking to Dad.
我喜欢她
l liked her.
她送了我一些可爱的浴盐
She gave me
some lovely bath salts.
－嘿，爸爸
－阿司匹林
￡- Hey, Dad.
￡- Aspirin.
马上拿来。听着……
Yeah, it's coming.
Listen￡-￡-
糟糕的圣诞节
Bad Christmas.
我跟你妈跳舞了
l danced
with your mother.
她说跟你跳舞的是垃圾桶
She said it was
the trash can.
我把她换了垃圾桶
l traded up
to the trash can.
好吧，听着
All right, listen,
你们打开我的礼物了没有？
did you guys open
my present?
什么？
What?
哦，打开了
Oh, yeah.
很不错，谢谢
very nice.
Thank you.
就这样？
你们看清是什么了吗？
That's it?
Did you see what it was?
什么？当然
What? Yeah.
是个面包机
lt was a toaster.
你们完全打开盒子了吗？
Did you open the box?
是的
Yeah.
你看见上面的字了？上面写了什么？
You saw what it said?
What did it say?
我不清楚
l don't know￡-￡-
“面包大师”
管他呢
"Toast Pro."
Who cares?
那是很特别的，那是件特别的礼物
lt was special.
lt's a special thing.
你们根本没打开盒子
你们应该打开看看的，爸爸
You didn't open the box.
You gotta open up the box, Dad.
它在哪？
Come on.
Where is it?
它……
l...
现在不在我身边
don't have it
with me right now.
什么意思？它在哪？
你们是不是把它处理掉了？
What do you mean? Where is it?
What did you do with it?
你妈妈想要个自动咖啡壶
Your mother wanted
a coffee￡-maker.
来了
Here we go.
你干了些什么？
What did you do?
我的面包机去哪了？
你们都做了什么啊？
Where is my toaster?
What did you do?
什么也没做，亲爱的
Nothing, dear.
当发现是个面包机时
我们就拿到了布鲁明戴尔商店
When we saw it was a toaster,
we took it over to Bloomingdale's
把它换成了一台咖啡机
and traded it in
for the coffee machine.
什么？但是我……
What, but, l￡-￡-
这根本不是从布鲁明戴尔商店买来的
it didn't even come
from Bloomingdale's.
店里不知道的
They don't know that.
那么你们骗了布鲁明戴尔？
So you lied
to Bloomingdale's?
不是骗布鲁明戴尔先生
Not Mr. Bloomingdale.
只是店里
Just the store.
什么时候去换的？
When did you do this?
你送给我们的当天
The day you gave it to us.
我不喜欢圣诞节后才去换礼品，人太挤了
l hate returning things after Christmas.
lt's so crowded.
－来点咖啡，亲爱的？
－不！不！
￡- Coffee, dear?
￡- No! No!
－我不要喝咖啡！
－味道不错的
￡- l don't want coffee!
￡- lt's very good.
那不是个普通的面包机，妈！
That wasn't just
a toaster, Ma.
它在说：“耶诞快乐，我们爱你”
lt said, "Merry Christmas.
We love you.
“麦克、杰弗瑞、艾丽、黛博拉和雷”
Michael, Geoffrey, Ally,
Debra and Ray."
它会说话？
lt spoke?
不！
No!
写在上面的！
On it!
在侧面，我把字刻在了侧面
On the side.
l had it engraved on the side!
－刻的？
－你刻字干什么？
￡- Engraved?
￡- What did you do that for?
我也不知道！
l don't know!
我原以为会很有意义
l thought it would
be nice.
我原以为你们会喜欢
l thought you might
enjoy it,
你们两个神经病！
you psychopaths!
那上面没我的名字？
Was my name on there?
我简直不敢相信！
你们知道我花了多少时间……
l can't believe this!
You know how much time and￡-￡-
－我原以为……
－亲爱的！
￡- and thought￡-￡-
￡- Sweetie, sweetie￡-￡-
－不……
－嘘～嘘
￡- No, it￡-￡-
￡- Shh, shh, shh.
听着，宝贝，听着
All right,
listen, honey, listen.
我理解你。我完全理解你的心情
l understand. l completely understand
why you're upset.
但让我说两句
But let me
explain something.
你看，这只自动咖啡壶
You see,
this coffee machine
会在早晨你起床之前就把咖啡煮好
has the coffee already made
when you come down in the morning.
那面包机上有你儿子的名字
The toaster has
your son's name,
还有他家人的名字
and the names
of his family,
你的孙子们
your grandchildren
还有他们的爱
都在上面
and their love on it.
对不起，亲爱的
l'm sorry, dear.
知道吗？
You know what?
也许我们可以在咖啡壶上也刻上名字
Maybe we can put the names
on the coffee machine.
话说回来，你干嘛买个面包机？
What are you buying
a toaster for anyway?
－旧的还能用
－不是的
￡- Ours is still good.
￡- No, it's not!
的确还能用，宝贝
lt is, dear.
你只是不会用
You just don't know
how to use it.
你得先轻轻摇一下
You've got to rattle it
a little bit.
然后再把面包拿出来翻个面
And then you pull the toast up
and turn it around
－这样就能烘到另外一面了
－这跟面包没关系
￡- and then do it on the other side.
￡- lt's not about toast!
我的礼物是有意义的
My gift had meaning.
每个人都喜欢我的面包机
除了你们之外，每个人都喜欢！
Everyone else loves the toaster!
Everyone else!
每个人！
Everyone!
你们究竟是些什么人啊！！
Who are you people?!
知道吗？每次我送你们礼物
You know what?
Any time l've ever given you a present,
－都是被好心当成驴肝肺
－怎么会？
￡- it's never been any good.
￡- That's not true.
－不是吗？那个微波炉
－哦，那个嘛
￡- No? The microwave.
￡- Well, that.
我们不需要微波炉
We didn't need
a microwave.
它们危害健康
And they're dangerous.
如果我还想要孩子怎么办？
What if l wanted
to have more children?
就算上帝答应，政府也不会答应的
lf God hasn't stopped you,
the government will.
还有那个月月水果俱乐部
What about the
Fruit￡-of-the￡-Month club?
那太疯狂了
That was insane!
一整年的水果？
A year of fruit?
他们到现在还给我寄宣传页
想叫我续会
You know they still send me
flyers wanting me to rejoin?
还有杏子的图片
And pictures of apricots!
－ 想想我会是什么感觉？
－ 你的感觉？
￡- How is that supposed to make me feel?
￡- How you feel?
那我的感受又如何呢？
你想过没有？
How about how l feel?
You ever think of that?
宝贝
Well, honey...
我们才是不得不收那些礼物的人哪
we are the ones who have
to get these presents.
我很抱歉
l'm sorry.
我不知道该说些什么了
l don't know
what else to say.
说“谢谢你”，怎么样？
How about thank you?
说“谢谢你”
Yeah, thank you.
正常人应该这么说
That's what people say.
我不管你们是不是需要面包机
也不管是不是浪费钱
l don't care if you need a toaster
or think it's a waste of money.
你们收到礼物，应该说声谢谢
You take the gift
and you say thank you.
知道为什么吗？
因为是我送的，我，雷蒙德！
And you know why?
Because it's from me! Me, me, Raymond!
你们的傻儿子雷蒙德！
Your idiot son Raymond!
他们怎么可能不喜欢面包机？
How could they not
like the toaster?
他们甚至都没打开盒子
They didn't even open it.
就把它换掉了
They traded it in.
没心没肺的精神病
Ungrateful mental cases.
也许问题的关键
You know, maybe
the question here
不是“他们为什么不喜欢我的礼物”
isn't, "Why don't they
ever like my presents?"
而是
but rather,
"Why do l
“为什么我那么渴望得到他们的赞赏”
so desperately need
their approval?"
啊！
Ah!
闭嘴！
Oh shut up!
闭嘴，换作是你你会有什么感觉？
Shut up!
How would you feel?
我会有什么感觉？
How would l feel?
也许你该读读我的书……
Maybe you'd like
to read my book￡-￡-
“在路上：罗伯特巴龙的故事”
"You're in the way:
The Robert Barone Story."
他不需要他们的赞赏
He doesn't need
their approval, sis.
他是个错误，他是被爱的
He's got it to a fault,
he's the beloved one.
他们爱我，在乎我
Oh yeah, they love me,
they care about me.
他们那样伤害我还叫什么在乎？
How come they don't care
that they hurt my feelings, huh?
你没亲身经历根本体会不到
That's right. You don't see them
doing anything about that!
－ 让我来说
－ 告诉他们实情就好了
￡- You let me do the talking.
￡- Just tell the truth.
不，不
No, no, no.
你从乡下来的？
Where are you from?
这面包机和咖啡壶我全要了
We walk out of here with the toaster
and the coffee thing.
什么？只要拿到雷蒙德的面包机就可以了
What?
Just get Raymond's toaster!
－请下一位
－嘘
￡- Next in line, please.
￡- Shh!
－别说什么……
－把嘴巴封起来，玛丽
￡- Just don't say anything that￡-￡-
￡- Lock it up, Marie!
哈喽
Hello.
－祝你圣诞快乐
－圣诞快乐
￡- And a merry Christmas to you!
￡- Merry Christmas.
主赐予福佑
May our Lord and Savior
bestow many blessings
给你和你的朋友
upon you and your
loved ones.
谢谢，我是犹太人
Thank you.
l'm Jewish.
哦
Oh.
这些人们肯定屁股很痛，嗯？
All these people
must be a pain in the ass, huh?
－弗兰克，别那么说！
－让我按自己的风格来
￡- Frank, don't say that!
￡- Let me do it my way.
－你们要退货吗？
－是的
￡- Are you returning this?
￡- Yes, we are.
这玩意是个破烂
lt unfortunately
is a piece of crap.
这很不错，我们只是想要点别的东西
lt's very nice.
We just would like something else.
－不！
－这个有什么问题吗？
￡- No!
￡- Was there something wrong with it?
我们甚至都没拆开
We didn't even
open it.
你帮倒忙啊！
This is how
you help?!
说谎是你的主意
Lying was
your idea.
我们今天为什么要说谎？
And why are we
lying today?
我的儿子送了这台咖啡壶
他是一番好意
My son brought us this coffee￡-maker,
and he means well,
但我们想换个真正用得上的东西
but we would like to change it
for something we can really use.
比如说……
You know, like a￡-￡-
l don't know,
一个面包机什么的
a toaster
or something?
好的，你们可以去那里挑一个
That's fine.
You can pick out a toaster over there.
太感谢你了
Thank you
very much.
拜拜
Shalom.
－ 我们本来可以两个都要的
－ 哦看哪，面包大师
￡- We could have got both!
￡- Oh look, Toast Pro.
打开这些盒子
Open these boxes.
－好的，好的
－找雷蒙德的面包机
￡- All right, all right.
￡- Just look for Raymond's toaster.
对不起，有什么能帮忙的吗？
l'm sorry.
May l help you?
我们自己能行，杰夫斯
We can handle it,
Jeeves.
我们想看一看
We're just checking these.
我保证这些和样品是一样的
l can assure you they're all exactly
like the display model.
瞧，这本说明书有点折了
See, here's one where the pamphlet's
a little folded.
你在干嘛？这根本不算是投诉
What are you doing?
That's not a believable complaint.
这完全合情合理
lt's perfectly valid.
你就不能安静一会吗？
Can't you ever
just be quiet?
别对我指手画脚的
Don't you tell me
to be quiet!
我自己拿主意，我能解决好的
l have a mind of my own, you know?
l can contribute.
我并不只是个天上掉下的林妹妹
l'm not just some
trophy wife!
你是天上掉下的林妹妹？
You're a trophy wife?
我到底中了什么破奖啊？
What contest in hell
did l win?
不好意思，你们把每个盒子都打开了
Please. You've opened
every box.
－我想问一下……
－你们不只有这些面包机吧？
￡- l'm going to have to ask￡-￡-
￡- This can't be every toaster.
是的，仓库里还有一些
No, l'm sure there are
more in the stockroom.
－仓库。拖住工作人员
－什么？
￡- Stockroom. Distract the workers.
￡- What?
继续唠叨就是了
Just keep yapping.
我的丈夫对面包很挑剔的
My husband is very particular
about his toast.
真他妈见鬼！
Holy crap!
我儿子送了我这台面包机
l got this toaster
for my son
作为圣诞礼物
for Christmas
yesterday,
但这上面有字
but it has
some writing on it.
噢，你要换掉这个吗？
Oh, are you
exchanging that?
不，我才不会换
No, l wouldn't dream
of exchanging it.
这是我儿子给我的
l got it
for my son.
换掉还算什么母亲
What sort of mother
would l be?
好吧……
Well...
如果是我我就会换掉它
看看那些字，傻得要命
l would exchange it because look
at that stupid writing on it.
但我喜欢
Oh but l love it.
只不过是店里把名字弄错了
The store just got
the names wrong.
能不能帮我改一下名字
Could you change
the names
改成“琼、哈维……
to June,
Harvey...
“波比……”
Bobby￡-￡-"
这面包机是我儿子雷蒙德的
You see, this toaster's
from my Raymond.
看看，我给你看，就是他
Look here.
Look, l'll show you. Here he is.
这是麦克
Look, see.
And there's Michael
杰弗瑞
and Geoffrey
还有艾丽
我倒是没有黛博拉的照片
and Ally and￡-￡-
l don't have a picture of Debra.
－把面包机给我，求你了
－不行，这是我儿子给我的
￡- Just give me that toaster, please.
￡- No, it's my son's.
但那是我儿子的，他需要我拥有这台面包机
But it's my son.
He needs me to have a toaster.
保安！
Security!
该死的累赘！
Stupid stinking hump!
嘿
Hey!
试试那个咖啡壶
Try a coffee machine.
是谁的电话？
Who was that?
雷，我想你最好去一趟布鲁明戴尔超市
Ray, l think you'd better get down
to Bloomingdale's.
显然，你的父母涉嫌卷入一起
Apparently, your parents are involved
in some sort of disturbance
毁坏财物，
involving destruction
of property
和盗窃面包机的案件
and the possible
theft of a toaster.
他们还是在乎的
They do care.
翻译：lisa doll
yukii45@hotmail.com
谢谢观赏